Okay, so who am I? Why should you care about anything I have to say? This is me. My name is John Bachy. I guess former software engineer. I've worked on trading chapops, thank you mobile apps, on this vehicle systems, tons of different things.
I know it is a developer advocate in a full-time tech enthusiast, hopefully powering developers, such as yourselves.
So they're doing to let me go over the agenda. So this is the beginner level. I'm sure probably 90% of the people in this room already know this stuff.
But I'll go over very quickly just to make sure anybody who doesn't code for a living is all caught up.
Then we have the more intermediate levels that we'll be going over.
This is where it actually starts to get more search engineering, S, and less computer science 101.
And then finally, we have the fun AI stuff, or AI adjacent in some cases.
So, yeah, let's get started.
All right, level one is in your search.
in a classroom and your deep player has asked you to get up on the arbitrary page.
One way you can do this is linearly, you could start to page one and then two, three, four, five.
I'm for you guys know that that's a horrible idea.
It would make you forever to do this.
It's awful, slow, group force, whole event.
More importantly, it doesn't leverage the fact that the book is ordered.
So the solution is binary search.
And probably this is closer to what you would actually do in the real world.
If you're aiming for page 72 and a 200 page book,
you'll probably start.
the middle, you can overshoot a little bit, go back, then go forward, go back, et cetera, et cetera,
until you hit page 72.
That's the way software will typically do search over an order of dataset, and that's what you do
in a, you know, in the real world with anything tangible.
And level three, hash tables. So if you want, go in with our book example, if you want to find out
what page two, uh, what page chapter two starts on, uh, you know that you can pop
open the book to the table of contents. So in this case, you can see I have a pizza cookbook here,
and chapter two starts on page 26. This is exactly the way half tables where it is a one-to-one
mapping between the data you have and the data you want. If I go to a code check,
and I get back the number 98, then I come back later that day. Whoever's manning the code
check knows which code is mine based off the number. License plate numbers,
social security numbers, credit card numbers, they all work basically the same way there.
A one-to-one mapping between data that you have and data that you want. This is the way
software works exactly. I'm not going to go into the
math of hash tables here, since that isn't totally relevant for our goals today, but
hopefully this is clear to anybody who doesn't work with software on a daily basis.
Okay, level four, inverted indices. So again, running with our book example and for the purposes
of everything that we're going to do today, let's just say that all of our examples are
going to be pizza related, which is, you know, fitting given what we're serving today.
So let's say that I need every pizza recipe in this book with mushrooms in it. How do I find that?
you know that you can open the back of the book and find the index. And just like that,
I now know that all the mushroom recipes are on page 34, 52, and 63. This is exactly the way an
inverted index works in a software system. If you are building out the search system for
your new email system and you need to let a user search for appointments, for example,
an inverted index can very easily find all of the emails that have mentions of the word appointment
in it. So unlike a hash table, it is not a one-to-one mapping, it's a one-to-many mapping, which,
if you're trying to build out a software system for search, that's, you know, usually pretty
relevant because you don't typically want just, you know, one result. You want the most relevant
50 or 500 results. So we're thinking about things in a one too many mapping makes more sense
as we, you know, get deeper and deeper into software research. Okay, level five, TF. TF is
a search algorithm and like all of the algorithms are going to go over today. They're very popular and based.
So let's break down the acronym. So TF stands for term frequency.
Pretty straightforward. What does that actually mean? It's just how often a term shows up in a document.
So if I have a recipe and, you know, the term, sorry, I'm going to blank on it, if the term
artichoke shows up 50 times in that document, the term frequency for that is going to be 50 or 5 or however many it's, you know, showing up there.
So again, I run a search for tasty artichoke pizza recipe, presumably in some
kind of recipe database system. And so how will the TF algorithm score different recipes
for this query? So I have recipe A and recipe B here. And you're probably immediately thinking,
why am I looking at a vanilla birthday cake recipe? I search for artichot pizza. It's not, you know,
birthday. Well, this author cleverly, you know, snuck in a couple of mentions of artichot pizza right
right there. The recipe is ultimately for birthday cake, but, you know, for the, for the event that
they're serving the birthday cake at or that they baked that they baked for, some of
be served artichoke pizza. So that's going to kind of mess up our search a little bit and why it's,
you know, we're even doing this comparison in the first place. So if we actually crunch these numbers
between this, you know, very minimal straight to the point recipe and, you know, sort of this keyword stuff
ones, we're going to get these numbers. And these are just counts of the number of time that these
different terms show up for each recipe. And just for clarity, why do we care? Why do we care about,
you know, why do we need a scoring algorithm? Well, it's because like I said before, we're, we're thinking
now in terms of getting back multiple results to our search queries. You don't
really ever want to have for users. This is the one or only artichoke pizza recipe I have.
I want to see all of the ones that you have. I want to see every artichot pizza recipe that you
have. And so you can see that if you count up these frequencies for each word that makes up our
user query, it doesn't look good. Recipe A got a total score of 12 and recipe B.5. So we are now
serving birthday cake recipes to our user who is for artichoke pizza recipes, which is
unfortunate and not great. So the natural question is how do we fix this? How are we going to
you know, win back this user. That is through another search algorithm known as IDF.
Like I said, we're going to be acronym heavy today, but I will break down all the acronym. So
what does IDF stand for? It stands for inverse document frequency. And what does that mean?
It's just how rare a term is in our database. So, for example, if I'm, you can think of it, like,
again, if we're going to run the cooking example, cheese is probably going to show up in a lot of
recipes. So it's not going to have a high IDF score. Cheese is going to be in, you know, however many
recipes, but if I'm, you know, if I want to sign an IDF score to a term like muscles or something,
that's probably only going to be in like seafood-based recipes, which is going to make a much
smaller subset of everything. So it's going to have a higher IDF score. So let's drill into a little
bit more, you know, what this means and how it works. So again, the frequency of a term is inversely
proportional to its IDF score, hence inverse documented frequency. Running with pizza again,
so let's think of terms that would have very low IDF stores. Slice, pie, peel.
Everybody in, you know, this room has heard of these terms. These are very common terms.
So they're going to get very low IDF scores. They are, they're not rare, and especially if we're
exclusively looking at pizza recipes. Now, if we look at char, hydration, crumb, now we're getting
into sort of pizza nerd territory. If you are a baker or, you know, you've got into making sourdough
during COVID, you've probably heard of these terms. And now if we go to leoparding,
poolish window paint, these are progressively even more advanced baking terms. These are not
something that you're going to see in.
you know, my weeknight, you know, pizza recipe or whatever, where it's like making pizza in 20 minutes,
this is something that really a baker would use in their terms. So we have two different algorithms
that TF and IDF. And I want to revisit recipe A, but now using both of these algorithms instead of
just the one. So again, just a review, recipe A got a TF score of 12 and recipe B got a TF score of
five. So in muting, these are these scores again. So recipe A, again, this is for cake.
How are we going to get these IDF scores for, you know, what the terms that the user put in?
Well, tasty and recipe are borderline useless. Probably every recipe in my database is going to have
the words Tasty and Recipe in it. So those are completely useless. They're going to be very common
across our entire recipe search database. So they're going to get very, very low IDF scores, most
likely. Now, artichoke and pizza are a little bit more rare. Artichoke especially doesn't, you know,
show up all that often in various recipes. And, you know, pizza is a common food, but it's not,
it's primarily only going to show up in the recipes that are for pizza and, you know, hopefully not birthday cake.
So what are we going to do? Now we have a TF score and an IDF score. We're going to multiply them and we're going to get the product for both of those scores.
We're going to add them up and we're going to get a new score, a final score of 19.2 in this case.
And so if we apply the same math to recipe B, which was actually for pizza, we get a score of 26.6. So this is much better. We want ultimately recipe B to rank higher than recipe A.
Recipe A is not what we want to give in this case. So presumably now, if I implement this in my recipe search system, a user is going to get recipe B up here and recipe A down here, which again, is what we want. Ideally, we don't want RESPA at all, but having a lower score is better than nothing. Okay, level 7, BM25. Again, new action. So BM25 stands for Best Match version 25. Why version 25? For my understanding, it's just the people that made the algorithm. It took them like 25 iterations to,
get to this particular version of the algorithm. So that's all it means.
So what is it? It's literally just TF and IDF with some more bells and whistles.
Let's go over those bells and whistles now by comparing two different hardichoke
piece of recipes. So. Yeah, yeah, you're good.
I'm sorry for the interruption. Fire Department is going to do some testing inspection today.
So you might hear the fire alarm go off. If it goes off, it's just the fire department doing some testing.
Okay, I'm very sorry for any convenience.
You're totally good. Thank you for letting us. Yeah.
Okay, so we have recipe B, which we just saw and recipe C, which is almost exactly the same.
They're both, you know, very minimal, but if you notice, there's some place, I've snuck in the bottom of this recipe here.
So instead of, you know, it's going to have more mentions of Ardichoke now because I'm mentioning other artichoke-based recipes here.
You know, good SEO, but not terribly good for, you know, search engineers.
Let's look at another recipe, recipe, recipe.
This is the exact same recipe. There is no difference. But again, this author here decided
to introduce the recipe with their time in Italy and all the different pizzas they try.
So now it's going to have more mentions of pizza in this case, which is not great.
BM25 is going to let us combat both of these scenarios directly. So improvements over TF and IDF.
A saturation curve is now applied to how term frequencies are calculated. And what exactly is a saturation
curve? I play this little video here. Okay, so all this really means is that you're going to
to see, yes, sorry. That kind of reminds of the viewer's number.
I'm sorry, I don't know what that is. It's in calculus. It's like, I forgot what it is.
It's around like 2.3 something. Oh, interesting. Okay. That was an intentional,
but that's, I guess, funny coincidence. In this case, all the saturation curve is really doing
is it means that you are going to see diminishing returns the number of times the word
work hard in show is mentioned. So if I mention it one time versus two times, that is going to
significantly move my score. If I mention it 27 versus 28 times, that's basically
going to do nothing to my PM 25 score. And this is useful because if I add 100 mentions
of artichoke at the end of my artichoke pizza recipe, that should not be a way for me to gain
whatever search system, you know, my recipe is going into. So that is essentially how the saturation
curve is working. The other improvement is that it's going to take document length into account.
So the guy that introduced his recipe with, you know, his time in Italy and all that thumb stuff
is no longer going to get the boost in our search system that he thinks he's going to get,
hopefully. Okay. Level 8, text analysis. Okay, so text analysis has a few different
forms, but it all starts with tokenization. Tokenization is all about breaking down a query into
individual tokens. Now, you might be thinking, why do we need to go over this? If someone's searching
for a tasty art to show pizza recipe, just use a white space delimiter, and I have four tokens,
done deal, don't need to think about it. The sense of that naïve
approach can work for some queries, but you're soon going to find that that doesn't work for
a lot of different queries that you're going to get. So let's take a couple of examples. So brick
oven pizza, am I including the hyphen or am I not including the hyphen? This will, you know,
meaningfully affect what results I'm getting back. If I type in how to make the research bar,
am I including the punctuation, do I want the question mark? And apostrophies, if I'm looking
for Danny's pizza, if that is a chef that has made a famous pizza recipe, or if that is the name
of a restaurant that I'm looking up, do I want the apostrophys?
or not. Other examples, in the Thai language, there are no spaces. And tie is not unique in this way.
There are other languages that don't have spaces. So in this case, if I want to get individual
tokens from that sentence there, I can't just use a white space limiter. That is not going to work.
If I am looking for path hierarchies, how am I, you know, handling forward slashes, backslashes,
things like that. Do I just want the root of that path? Do I want the pull path? And if there's an
email in there, this can really trip me out.
I chose, for whatever reason, depending on the input I'm getting, to delimit by periods, or anything else like that.
You know, I want that full email there. I don't want it to get garbled.
And in this case, we are using various tokenizers from elastic that are particularly tuned to specific inputs.
So this is much of a technical concern is that it is a U. What kind of data are you expecting from your users?
Okay, stop words in the next phase of text analysis.
These are words like B of and as are, these are obviously language.
but essentially they're all unhelpful filler. These words don't meaningfully tell us anything
about what the user is searching for. Normally the way that our search systems are going to work
is we're just going to filter them out and not do anything with them.
Stemming. Okay, so in the same vein, if I am looking up charred pizza, I don't care if someone's recipe
says this pizza will have char on it or I want lots of char on my pizza. I just want that concept.
It doesn't matter to me how it's articulated. So the way that we typically handle this in
systems is using something called stemming where you basically truncate a word to its root
form, it's stem form is a word. So in this case, charred pizza is going to become char
pizza in, you know, African organization. Synonyms. So it does not matter whether I'm looking
for New York or NMI or NMI or NY style pizza. I want the same recipes. I shouldn't have to manually
input all of those search terms to get back the actual recipes that I want. How are we going
to do this? In Elastic, there are a couple of ways to achieve this. You can use the synonyms API.
You can use the synonyms file and you can do this inline with the token filter.
And I'll show those examples here.
So you can see both for the synonyms API and the synonyms file.
Essentially, all you're doing is defining a dictionary in a file or a set,
like this for that as these synonyms.
We can also do an inline here, which is basically what that is.
There's a fire alarm.
So you can see that Newark is just an honest of NLIN once.
Again, you can't like do this like blanket.
In this case, if I'm building a pizza search engine, search engine,
then, you know, that is something that I can reasonably anticipate that's going to happen.
So again, this is as much of a technical concern as that is a UX concern at the end of the day.
And spell chest.
So if a user mistypes, you know, what they, pizza as P IZA, I do not want to give back results for PISA.
Those are probably going to be nonsense, you know, garbled stuff.
And I want to be able to handle that.
I'm sure all of you have seen this in your perverts or attention.
So how can we do this?
You can register incorrect spellings as synonyms.
You can use fuzzy queries, which operate through,
11GD distance, which I'm not going to go over today, but I imagine a lot of you are familiar with it.
And if not, it's, it's fairly easy to pick up.
A system in elastic called suggestors and phonetic token filter plugins, which essentially work by
breaking down words into how they are pronounced.
So if a user knows how a word is pronounced, they don't know how to spell it, you can still get a
match potentially.
All right, let's put that all together.
So I search for the best wood-fired Neapolitan pie.
First, I want to get rid of though.
That's a stop.
that's not relevant to what I want to search for.
It's completely useless.
Next, I want to do stemming.
So fired is now going to become fire.
Pie is a synonym for pizza pie.
I don't want to get results about Apple Pie or something like that.
That is not going to be helpful for this user.
And lastly, I don't know if anyone caught at Neapolitan.
That's supposed to be a pay.
So to review, we remove the stopwords.
We converted words into their stem form.
We expanded synonyms, so pie is now pizza.
And we performed.
a basic spell check.
Okay, level nine, re-rankers.
So how would search work in an ideal world?
And that's like a legitimate question.
That's not rhetorical.
Like, if you actually think about it for a second,
how would you imagine search working in an ideal world?
I don't know about you guys, but in my ideal world,
there's one guy, read Ranker.
And what this guy does is he will get all irrelevant documents for me.
So if I search for art of choked pizza recipe,
he's going to go in the back and pull out all the documents.
And then he's going to read them.
He's going to read each one.
And he's going to rank them individually by, you know, by relevance.
You have one person essentially doing all of this work.
This is obviously not possible.
But we can just do this for the first few entries.
So, again, if we think about this from a UX perspective,
users are typically not going to page 24 of your search results,
you know, try to find the perfect entry.
It's been proven time and time again that they are spending the most time on page one,
maybe page two or three, potentially four,
but after that there's a very, very steep drop-off in users engaging with the,
essentially the search results of giving them back.
So what have we optimized for that?
read is still too slow.
One person cannot do this.
But a machine learning model isn't.
So what we can do, and this is essentially how re-rankers operate,
is that Reed is still doing exactly what he's doing.
He can, you know, grab, let's say, if I ask him,
hey, Reed, give me the top, you know, the top artichoke pizza recipes.
He can give me the top 10 in ranked order and feed that into a machine learning model
or train it in a variety of different ways.
And essentially what the re-ranker will do,
we'll just do a final pass-through on
on the very first page.
So the re-ranker isn't operating over the entire, I guess,
return set for the search results.
It's just giving page one a little bit extra finesse, so to speak.
So I know I've been throwing a lot of you guys.
We've been moving very quickly, so I want to sort of illustrate
how all of this works with one query,
all of these concepts and levels that we've been running through.
So charred, crust, artichoke pizza recipe.
First, we're going to do text analysis.
We need to break this up into tokens.
We're going to do a basic analysis.
spell correct. P-I-ZA is obviously incorrect. It's supposed to be P-I-Z-ZA. And again,
charred is going to become charred. We're going to use an inverted index. An inverted index is going
to grab every recipe filed under Artichoke, for example. So now we have a subset of recipes
that are potentially relevant to, you know, what the, what the user is for. Next, we're going to use
BM25. So we have, let's say, 100 recipes. We don't want to give them back to the user in a
random order. We want them to be scored in an intelligent way. So we're going to use a combination of
TF and IDF, plus the other bells and wishes that we talked about that BM25 comes with.
And lastly, we're going to have a re-ranker come in at the end and reorganize the first few entries
so that they just look a little nicer that they're presented, you know, a little bit more cleanly.
Any questions so far? That is basically everything that we have gone through. We still have a little
bit more to go, but I just want to have a little checkpoint here to see if there are any
questions, comments, concerns, kind of thing. Okay, cool. Moving right along.
Level 10 vectors. Okay, a vector is how a computer,
encodes abstract concepts. This is kind of a gross over simplification, but hopefully we will
get to a more concrete understanding by the end of this level. And I'm going to use Italian-American
cuisine as my example here. So we're still running with, you know, pizza or pizza-adjacent
examples. So let's say I graph, you know, a handful of different Italian-American foods
along this simplex. How do you read this? What exactly is this? So basically, each food is
going to be closer to the vertex that corresponds with that ingredient and farther away from the
vertices that represent ingredients that are not present in that feed. So in this case,
garlic knots are basically all dough, maybe there's a little bit of cheese, so they're going to be a little
lifted cook over there. Monterella sticks are basically just breaded cheese. So they're essentially
going to hug the left side there if you, you know, don't get any marinara on the side,
there's going to be no tomato involved. If it's all tomato, it's marinero. And if it's
different parts, dough, cheese, and tomato, it's going to be pizza, lasagna, and stuff shells in the
center. They're roughly equidistant from all three of these. And obviously,
vectors are not going to, you know, make you a nice pretty diagram. These are going to be,
you know, graphed in vector space. So there's going to be a coordinate system that this corresponds
to. Now, unfortunately, I can't, you know, encode every single cuisine in the known universe,
you know, along this small simplex. I can barely do Italian-American cuisine. I'm not considering
whether protein is an element of the dish or really any other ingredients. So this is a gross
over-sympification. In reality, this is going to look something like this. It's going to be along 100 or
1,000 dimensions. And I'm not going to be plotting these manually. I'm going to be using an
embedding model or, yeah, an embedding model, and it's going to generate these vectors for me.
And the way that they're going to be plotted is not going to be along human-readable axes. They're
going to be, you know, only really machine intelligence. They're not really going to be,
you know, relevant to what we can read, but this is a very helpful way to understand what concepts
are and are not related. So just by visually looking at this, you can tell that Votkasas and Maranara,
even if you don't know what those things are, you can tell that they're
you know, roughly similar. Same idea with stuffed shells and lasagna. You can also tell
if things are really far apart that they're not related. Garlic knots and vodka sauce essentially don't
really have all that much in common, which is useful. And we can do this just by measuring, you know,
doing some basic math and measuring the distance in coordinate space. It's a lot easier to do if it's,
three coordinates, much harder to do if it's 100 or thousands of coordinates, but, you know,
you're obviously not doing that math manually. Okay, so why do we care about vectors? Why did I go over that?
what is the point of this? And how does that help us with search? That is what hybrid search is here to answer.
So hybrid search is the fusion of BM25 vector-based search. Essentially, we are still doing
everything that we talked about before. We are not abandoning it. I'm going to emphasize that every level
that I've been going over is essentially additive. You don't really abandon any of those strategies.
You just keep stacking them on top of each other to make a more comprehensive search system,
essentially. How are these going to be merged? That's through an algorithm called reciprocal
range fusion or RF. I'm not going to go over the math. We don't have the time for that,
but essentially I just want you to take away that this is the algorithm that is essentially
how we're going to merge these two disparate search systems. So this is what we went over before.
This is still, like I said, this is the entire system. It still functions basically the exact same
way, and except we are going to have BM25 and vector work together. And so how does this
work practically in a search system? Imagine that your user,
for whatever reason has never heard of the concept of pizza. And they're like, hey, I had this cheesy
flatbread. Give me a recipe for that. Vectors are what is ultimately going to help you
or help your search system understand that cheesy flatbread is a synonym for pizza. You can't do that
with BM25. BM25 is not going to work with things that are sort of that abstract.
BM25 is great for things that are more literal, more, you know, exact keyword match-esque.
Vector is good for conceptual understanding, things that are conceptually related.
but maybe aren't direct synonyms. So it's not that you always want to use hybrid search or you exclusively
want to use BM25 or exclusively vector. These are, these are system dependent. It depends on
what are your user searching for. I talk to people every single day about, you know,
how they're building their search systems, their rack systems. And I see this common
misunderstanding that you sort of have to, you know, there's one definitive way to build out these
search systems and that just doesn't work that way. It is always going to be dependent on the type of data that you
cows. So for this presentation, I've primarily been going over recipes, specifically
pizza recipes, for the most part, but this is always, you are always going to tweak this basic
setup depending on what kind of data that you have. Do you know fundamental building blocks
that you're going to be working? Okay, level 12, rag. So what is rag? Again, I'm breaking
down every acronym here for treval augmented generation. This is probably the term that I see
really misused the most often. So I have seen people point to specific tooling or
specific architectures as being rag-based and I think that is a bit of a misnomer and sort
of playing fast and loose with the vocabulary. All rag is is a way to augment LOMs with something
retrieval-based. That's all it is. It is a very large umbrella term. So why do we need this? Why
why do we care about this? So imagine that I have an L-O-M. It doesn't matter whether it's Gemini or
clot or whatever, but let's just say it was trained in 2025. A ton of data was fed into it in 2025.
But I'm asking for the best pizza recipe of 2026. There is no way for that LOM to give me that data
through, you know, just through generation. It doesn't, it doesn't know about it. It'd be like asking
Isaac Newton, who's going to win the summer, you know, Olympics of 1996. It does not matter how smart
Isaac Newton is. He does not have that information and he cannot give it to you.
It applies to an LOM. It does not matter how smart it is, how intelligent it is. It cannot give you
that information. That is what the retrieval portion is essentially here in fix. So everything that we saw
in that. So if you look at steps two, retrieve, and then it goes to the web. It's essentially
doing all of this. All of this is happening behind the scenes for any kind of LOM to essentially
crawl the web, read everything, rank it accordingly, and determine what to get back to you.
And that's essentially how it works. So it would do all of that, you know, that whole pipeline
that we just discussed, and that's how it would give you back that data. Okay, level 13,
agentic memory. This functions very similar.
And I also see people regularly talk about this in a way that I think both of these things or describes this in a way that isn't technically accurate.
All this is really doing is making up for the fact that your LOM, whatever LOM you prefer, has a limited context window.
So it does not matter if LOM's tomorrow have, you know, a context window this big or this big.
At some point, it will reach a limit on that, and it's going to need to search through some kind of conversation history to remember that.
So let's say that I'm talking to an LOM for like an LOM for like an NAC.
hour about making, you know, a bunch of, and my own custom artichot pizza recipe.
And I say, hey, do you remember that pickle pizza recipe you made for me earlier?
Let's say that was like an hour ago.
That might not be in the LOM's context window anymore.
And it needs to go back into it's our conversation history and search through all of it.
So again, it is going to be doing this entire process along our own conversation history in order
to give me back that pickle pizza recipe that I had generated earlier.
Now, I'm not claiming that this is exactly.
how chatGVT or whatever does it, but this is the basic principle behind how it works.
The same thing for RAG.
I can't tell you exactly how your favorite RAG system works.
All I'm trying to elucidate is that these are fundamentally the basic building blocks that you would need for these sort of systems.
And that's basically it.
Are there any questions?
Okay.
Thank you so much.
Let me check in with our second speaker.
I'm here.
Yeah, absolutely.
Sorry, I didn't notice that you came in.
John, I asked, how do we decide, like, which I'm going to come or which type of search we wanted to go for?
Throughout the way we are trying to improve our search, there might be vector search, which might be working best in a one use case.
Should we go ahead with the hybrid search, or should we stay with the vector search?
Gotcha.
So, again, it's all going to be dependent on what kind of,
the, I guess, say that your users are searching for.
So let's say that you are Walmart and you want to create a search system.
If this is like an internal database and you want people to be able to search by my product ID,
excuse me, product ID is not going to work well with vectors.
Product ID does not make sense for that.
You want BM25 for that because that is a very specific, like, keyword-esque thing.
You are looking at a string literal.
Encoding product IDs into a vector database does not make any sense.
But if you want someone to search for,
I'm looking for a plastic do-hickey with four legs and a flat surface because I don't remember the word for table.
That is something that vectors would be good at.
Vectors are good at conceptually linking those two ideas together.
So again, it really just depends on what kind of queries you're expecting.
If it's exact match, you want BM-25, or if it's close to exact match.
If you want something a little bit more vague, a little bit more conceptual, you can do vectors.
And if it might be both, then hybrid is probably the way to go.
I would say that in the majority of cases that I see,
hybrid is probably, you know, the way to go.
But even then, you still raise other questions about, like,
how much do you want to go with hybrid,
or how much do you want to go with Vector versus how much do you want to go with BM25?
So it's all just going to depend.
You also recommend that for like documentation, like search for thoughts?
Yeah, I would say that if you, if you want somebody to get,
like, the documentation is very specific.
It's very precise.
In that case, I would probably say that if you want to lean more towards like BM25 instead of vectors,
for example.
I'm sorry.
I couldn't get it.
What's the tax for hybrid?
The tax for hybrid?
It takes longer.
You are running two parallel searches essentially,
so it's going to take that much longer.
And on top of that, you also need to run the RRF algorithm
to merge them together.
So there is, you know, then you start getting
to questions about latency, is it's worth it,
things like that, so yeah,
nothing comes, nothing comes for you unfortunately.
So it's like 2x, 3x.
I don't want to lie to you.
Honestly, I'm not exactly sure about, like, the exact number.
Again, it would depend on how you're waiting the two different, two different ones.
So if it's like a 50-50 split versus like 60-40, that's going to meaningfully affect things,
also depends on how many dimensions that your vectors are being embedded in.
Is it 100, you know, dimensions?
Is it 700?
Is it 2,000 that's also going to, you know, meaningfully affect things?
There's just way too many variables for me to be able to give you, like, a clear answer on that.
Is there a way to cut off one if it looks like the other one is kind of a different?
results?
Yeah, so you can implement systems where you're determining at like runtime, if a user
searches for something, you can have ways of determining, oh, this looks like it would be better
for vector search, this would be better for BM25, or this would be better for hybrid,
So you can make, you know, semi-intelligent guesses about which of those methods might work the best
under different conditions.
Oh, any other questions?
All right, awesome.